<book 
	xmlns='http://docbook.org/ns/docbook' 
	xmlns:xlink='http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink'
	version="5.0" xml:lang="en">
<title>From Docbook to ePub and Kindle</title>
<info>
	<author>
		<personname>
			<firstname>Carlos</firstname>
			<surname>Araya</surname>
		</personname>
	</author>
	<mediaobject role="cover">
		<imageobject>
			<imagedata fileref="images/docbook.png" format="PNG"/>
		</imageobject>
	</mediaobject>
</info>

<chapter xml:id="rethinking.the.future.of.books">
	<title>Rethinking the future of books</title>
	<subtitle>Random thoughts on books as artifacts</subtitle>

	<para>With the introduction of all iPads and other tablet readers we are left with some big question: Are books still relevant? If they are still relevant, how do they need to change?</para>

	<para>Craig Mod has written and spoken about the future of books and what we can do with books online with the new technologies for both creating the content and financing the production of the content. It caught my attention for a variety of reasons. How do we leverage the new technologies for books and the new devices we use to read these new books. </para>

<mediaobject>
	<videoobject>
		<videodata fileref="video/do-lectures.mp4"/>
		<multimediaparam name="controls" value="controls"/>
	</videoobject>
	<imageobject role="poster">
		<imagedata fileref="video/do-lectures.png"/>
	</imageobject>
	<textobject>
		<para>Craig Mod presenting at the Do Lecture in 2010</para>
	</textobject>
</mediaobject>

<para>Some of the things that caught my attention:</para>

<sect1>
	<title>New ways to produce content</title>

	<para>We can create more interactive content as part of our books. The new ePub 3 standard includes multimedia content (audio and video) as part of what we put in our books. While iBooks uses a somewhat different format than the standard ebook format it already allows for the inclusion of audio and video.</para> 

	<para>We can incorporate external video or we can produce our own as part of the book creation process. Whichever way we choose this prompts a new way of thinking about books. If we can embed multimedia content directly into books, how are they now different than regular web pages? Sure, we can't embed java applets or flash video but we can easily link to pages on the web that have the content.</para>

	<para>Are we requiring our users to be constantly online in order to interact with our content? If we add multimedia content to a book, does it mean that users have to be online while reading? For most tablets this is not an issue as internet connectivity is bundled with the device. As designers, however, we need to keep in mind that not all users have wireless connectivity for their devices. </para>

	<para>Using <link xlink:href="http://craigmod.com/bibliotype/">Bibliotype</link> as a starting point we can explore alternatives and options for putting content into web browsers and other devices without having to author a full eBook. </para>
</sect1>
<sect1>
	<title>What tools do we use to create the content?</title>

	<para>One of the things that attracted me to creating ePub content is the variety of tools that are available to do so. Starting with  relatively simple tools like Sigil or Pages to create ePub content we can get as sophisticated as we want or need to be. tools like iBook Creator can provide a high level of sophistication at the expense of being cross platform. </para>

	<para>For those of us used to creating multiple versions of a document using an XML base; it is good to know that tools like Docbook can now create ePub 2 and ePub 3 content from the same basic XML document that we have used to create HTML and PDF versions of our content in the past. </para>

	<para>Whatever tools we use we need to decide if the multimedia features or access to our content by a specific device make it worthwhile to create multiple versions of our content</para>
</sect1>
<sect1>
<title>Project funding as a means of engagement</title>

	<para>We can use sites like <link xlink:href="http://kickstarter.com/">Kickstarter</link> as both a fund raising site and as a way to engage our community of users. </para>

	<para>Kickstarter allows content creators to setup their project with the following parameters:</para> 

	<itemizedlist>
		<listitem><para>A description of the project</para></listitem>
		<listitem><para>The fundraising steps/stages both the amount and what benefit do you derive</para></listitem>
		<listitem><para>The amount to be raised and how long we have to do it</para></listitem>
		<listitem><para>A discussion area for the project</para></listitem>
	</itemizedlist>

	<para>Kickstarter acts like an escrow service. If the full amount is raised in the allocated time then each individual contributor's credit card will be charged for the amount they pledged; otherwise nothing happens. </para>

	<para>More than fund raising, Kickstarter allows you to create a community around your project. It's not just the monetary support that brings the supporters together. They are interested in seeing the project funded and completed for whatever reason they have. They are your funding agency or agencies and they can be your sounding board and your reality check when needed.</para>

	<para>Another interesting site is <link xlink:href="http://www.indiegogo.com/">Indiegogo</link> which provides one additional feature that I find interesting: The option of flexible funding where you get all the fund pledged by the target date regardless of whether you met your fundraising goal or not.</para>  
</sect1>
<sect1>
	<title>How do we engage with book in a digital format?</title>

	<para>Seth Godin asks the question:</para>

	<blockquote>
	<para>What happens when a publisher has a tight, direct connection with readers, is able to produce intellectual property that spreads, and can do both quickly and at low cost?<footnote xml:id="source1"><para>Seth Godin created the <link xlink:href="http://www.thedominoproject.com/about">Domino project</link> as a way to put the publishers closer in contact with their audiences. This is one of the questions he asks on the site.</para></footnote></para> 
	</blockquote>

	<para>We have to start by accepting that, in this context, we are all publishers and we all have networks or hives of people who can support us in our creative endeavors. Being exposed to feedback early and often is a great way to eliminate uncertainty and provide a sounding board even before the project actually begins.<footnote xml:id="fields"><para>See chapter 5 and 6 in Jonathan Field's book <link xlink:href="http://www.theuncertaintybook.com/">Uncertainty</link> for more on creating hives and using them as support mechanisms.</para></footnote></para>
</sect1>
<sect1>
<title>Blogs as book drafts</title>

	<para>We are not only publishers but we're experts as well. For those of us who blog or maintain a professional or business related website the expertise is right there. We can use blogs to author content, to measure interest based on comments and get feedback from our hive of users.</para>

	<para>Does this work for everyone? Probably not. After all we are not all alike in the way we handle criticism and feedback for something that's not necessarily complete and in a way we'd like people to see it and comment on. </para>

	<para>But that's they key... it is not ready which means that the feedback we get at the early stages of the project will allow us to change the content or even change the project we are working on and this will definitely make the project better.</para>
</sect1>
<sect1>
	<title>Creating multiple delivery methods from the same content</title>

	<para>When I first started working with <link xlink:href="http://docbook.org/">Docbook</link> one of the things that attracted me to it was the fact that from the same source, using different XSLT style sheets you can produce different formats for your document. </para>

	<para>In the last couple years, the Docbook community has expanded the range of formats and it now includes ePub3. It's easier than ever to create content in a document neutral format and then convert it to HTML, PDF and ePub without bigger effort than creating customizations to the stock <link xlink:href="http://docbook.sourceforge.net/">style sheets</link> which we can then reuse on future projects.</para>
</sect1>
</chapter>

<chapter xml:id="accessibility">
  <title>Accessibility, Epub and You</title>
  
  <para></para>
</chapter>

<chapter xml:id="publishing">
<title>Publishing your content</title>

<para>This is where we talk about publishing your content yourself, publishing to Amazon and, maybe, to the iBooks store</para>
</chapter>


<chapter xml:id="looking.forward">
    <title>Looking forward: What's next?</title>
    <sect1>
        <title>Pushing the boundaries of EPub</title>
    <para>EPub 3 also opens the door to further bluring of the difference between books, web sites and web applications. Part of the EPub specification is the Fixed Layout Documents (the specification is available at <link xlink:href="http://idpf.org/epub/fxl/">http://idpf.org/epub/fxl/</link>) that allow for absolute positioning of content, 1 or 2-page spreads, text overlays and other neat publishing tricks and effect.</para>
    
    <para>fully exploring what we can do with an epub book, specifically content switching (<link xlink:href="http://idpf.org/epub/30/spec/epub30-contentdocs.html#sec-xhtml-content-switch">http://idpf.org/epub/30/spec/epub30-contentdocs.html#sec-xhtml-content-switch</link>) and scripting epub books (See more below for scripting)</para>
    
    <para>Media Overlays can add synchronized audio to the text. <link xlink:href="http://idpf.org/epub/30/spec/epub30-mediaoverlays.html">http://idpf.org/epub/30/spec/epub30-mediaoverlays.html</link></para>
    
    <para>How far can we script an EPub book without limiting the readers that can access our content? Epub3 already supports scripting (<link xlink:href="http://idpf.org/epub/30/spec/epub30-contentdocs.html#sec-scripted-content">http://idpf.org/epub/30/spec/epub30-contentdocs.html#sec-scripted-content</link>) and scripts (JavaScript) are a basae media type for EPub3. Can we use JQuery and if so how much of the JQuery featurse set can we use on our EBooks?</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Modular Docbook and Collaborative writing</title>
        <para>So far we have only created one big file for our book content. Docbook also allows the creation of modular content; the idea is that we create one main file where all out chapters or other chunks of content are in a single monolythic file. In order to make our lives easier we have two alternatives for modularizing the content: Collaborate using Git and creating modular Docbook documents.</para>
        
        <sect2>
          <title>Collaborative writing using Git.</title>
        
        <para>We can use tools such as <link xlink:href="https://github.com">Github</link> to maintain a wirting collaborative. With tools like this we are no longer limited to manual updates; all collaborators can stay up to date with what everything else is doing by downloading the content of the book and updating periodically. If there is disagreement it can be hammered out as the book is being written and read by everyone rather than at the end of the process when changes are costlier and people are invested in the book as is.<footnote><para>The XML source for this book along with all the ancillary files (Ant build files and others) are available on Github at <link xlink:href="https://github.com/caraya/docbook-epub">https://github.com/caraya/docbook-epub</link></para></footnote></para>
        
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
          <title>Modular Docbook</title>
          
          <para>Docbook offers you </para>
        </sect2>
    </sect1>
    
    <sect1 xml:id='crowdsourcing'>
      <title>Kickstarter, Indiegogo and crowdfunding your work</title>
      
      <para>Even the funding may be community supported. Services like <link xlink:href="http://www.kickstarter.com/">Kickstarter</link> or <link xlink:href="http://www.indiegogo.com/">Indiegogo</link> provide "crowd funding" platforms where people who are interested in your idea can invest in it even before the product is completed.</para>

      <para>There are few differences between Kickstarter and Indiegogo; The biggest difference is that Indiegogo allows for partial funding. Say that we decided to raise $1000 for our book but, for whatever reason, we failed to meet the target. Kickstarter will consider the drive failed and no money will be charged to the people who did sign up. With the flexible option, Indiegogo will charge the amount raised up to that point from the people who pledged their donations.</para>

      <para>Now you get no only the funding you need to get your book up and running but you also get a group of enthusiastic people who are as interested in the success of your book as you are, if not more<footnote><para>For a more detailed account of a successful Kickstarter story see Craig Mod's <link xlink:href="http://craigmod.com/journal/kickstartup/">Kickstartup</link> essay.</para></footnote>.</para>
    </sect1>
</chapter>

<bibliography>
<title>References</title>

<bibliomixed>
	<bibliomset relation='blog'>Godin, Seth.
		<title role='blog'><emphasis>The Domino Project</emphasis></title>.
	</bibliomset>
	<bibliomset relation='website'>
		[Available online] at <link xlink:href="http://sethgodin.typepad.com/seths_blog/2010/12/the-domino-project.html">http://sethgodin.typepad.com/seths_blog/2010/12/the-domino-project.html</link>.
	</bibliomset>
</bibliomixed>

<bibliomixed>
	<bibliomset relation='blog'>Godin, Seth.
		<title role='blog'><emphasis>Moving On</emphasis></title>.
	</bibliomset>
	<bibliomset relation='website'>
		[Available online] at <link xlink:href="http://sethgodin.typepad.com/seths_blog/2010/08/moving-on.html">http://sethgodin.typepad.com/seths_blog/2010/08/moving-on.html</link>.
	</bibliomset>
</bibliomixed>

<bibliomixed>
	<bibliomset relation='article'>Mod, Craig.
		<title role='article'><emphasis>Books in the age of the iPad</emphasis></title>.
	</bibliomset>
	<bibliomset relation='website'>
		[Available online] at <link xlink:href="http://craigmod.com/journal/ipad_and_books/">http://craigmod.com/journal/ipad_and_books/</link>.
	</bibliomset>
</bibliomixed>

<bibliomixed>
	<bibliomset relation='article'>Mod, Craig.
		<title role='article'><emphasis>Embracing the digital book</emphasis></title>.
	</bibliomset>
	<bibliomset relation='website'>
		[Available online] at <link xlink:href="http://craigmod.com/journal/ebooks/">http://craigmod.com/journal/ebooks/</link>.
	</bibliomset>
</bibliomixed>

<bibliomixed>
	<bibliomset relation='article'>Mod, Craig.
		<title role="article"><emphasis>Kickstartup: Successful fundraising with Kickstarter.com &amp; (re)making Art Space Tokyo</emphasis></title>.
	</bibliomset>
	<bibliomset relation='website'>
		[Available online] at <link xlink:href="http://craigmod.com/journal/kickstartup/">http://craigmod.com/journal/kickstartup/</link>.
	</bibliomset>
</bibliomixed>

<bibliomixed>
	<bibliomset relation='article'>Mod, Craig.
		<title role='article'><emphasis>The shape of our future book</emphasis></title>.
	</bibliomset>
	<bibliomset relation='website'>
		[Available online] at <link xlink:href="http://craigmod.com/satellite/our_future_book/">http://craigmod.com/satellite/our_future_book/</link>.
	</bibliomset>
</bibliomixed>

<bibliomixed>
	<bibliomset relation='blog'>Rusch, Kristine Kathryn.
		<title role='blog'><emphasis>Quality</emphasis></title>.
	</bibliomset>
	<bibliomset relation='website'>
		[Available online] at <link xlink:href="http://kriswrites.com/2012/03/21/the-business-rusch-quality/">http://kriswrites.com/2012/03/21/the-business-rusch-quality/</link>.
	</bibliomset>
</bibliomixed>

<bibliomixed>
	<bibliomset relation='book'>Stayton, Bob.
 		<title role='book'><emphasis>XSL: The Definitive Guide</emphasis></title>.
	</bibliomset>
	<bibliomset relation='website'>
		[Available online] at <link xlink:href="http://www.sagehill.net/docbookxsl/">http://www.sagehill.net/docbookxsl/</link>.
	</bibliomset>
</bibliomixed>

<bibliomixed>
	<bibliomset relation='book'>Walsh, Norman.
		<title role='book'><emphasis>DocBook 5.1: The Definitive Guide</emphasis></title>.
	</bibliomset>
	<bibliomset relation='website'>
		[Available online] at <link xlink:href="http://docbook.org/tdg51/en/html/">http://docbook.org/tdg51/en/html/</link>.
	</bibliomset>
</bibliomixed>
</bibliography>
</book>