<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<book 
	xmlns='http://docbook.org/ns/docbook' 
	xmlns:xlink='http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink'
	version="5.0" xml:lang="en">
<title>From Docbook to ePub and Kindle</title>
<info>
	<author>
		<personname>
			<firstname>Carlos</firstname>
			<surname>Araya</surname>
		</personname>
	</author>
	<!-- Required to have the image show on the ebook reader cover --> 
	<mediaobject role="cover">
		<imageobject>
			<imagedata fileref="images/docbook.png" format="PNG"/>
		</imageobject>
	</mediaobject>
</info>
<preface xml:id="preface">
<title>Publishing for everyone</title>

<blockquote><para><emphasis role="bold"><emphasis>"Much is to be gained by eBooks: ease, convenience, portability. But something is definitely lost: tradition, a sensual experience, the comfort of thingy-ness — a little bit of humanity." (Chip Kidd)</emphasis></emphasis></para></blockquote>

<para>Publishing is no longer the province of big publishers or that crazy people who dream of writing a book and find out that the only way to get published is to do it themselves. Well, we all can publish our work with tools like Docbook,  formats like ePub and publishers like Amazon.</para>

<para>We all have something to publish. We all have something to tell the world.</para>

<para>I chose to publish my content using Docbook because of it's flexibility. While we're talking only about ePub and Kindle publishing, Docbook can generate a variety of other formats using the same tools that we are using to generate our ePub content. You can learn more about Docbook and the associated XSLT style sheets at <link xlink:href="http://www.docbook.org/">http://www.docbook.org/</link>.</para>

<para>This e-book seeks to answer questions that, to me, are essential to a successful publishing endeavor:</para>

<itemizedlist>
	<listitem>Why should I publish my own content?</listitem>
	<listitem>Is an Ebook the right solution?</listitem>
	<listitem>Why should I use Docbook to do it?</listitem>
	<listitem>How do I create my ebook using these tools?</listitem>
</itemizedlist>

<para>In answering these questions my hope is that you will create new content and give it to the world. I'm sure we'll all be much better for it</para>

</preface>


<chapter xml:id="create">
<title>Why should I create an ebook? Why with Docbook?</title>
<para>Again, We all have something to say to the world. And ebooks make it easier than ever to have the world as your audience. Whatever form your message takes we can build a book and a community around it. We have different technologies to communicate before, during and after creating our content and we are given plenty of opportunities to engage with our readers during the process.</para>

<para>Take bloggers for example. We can leverage our blog as a development platform for written content with multiple drafts and selectively, based on the feedback received from readers, can use the best content as part of our book or books. We have not only authored the content of the book months or years in advance but we have also built a community of people who are vested in the content we author.</para>

<para>We can also engage the community as co-authors of our content. With proper clearance we can edit the users' comments into the narrative that we initially wrote on our blog and weave a fuller narrative about our content. We can further refine the content by making the result of our collaboration available to the community and further edit the book thus it becoming a living document that evolves according to what the community sees as new or interesting. </para>

<para>I don't know about you but I've always dreamed of writing the great big novel. Now it's within our reach. We don't have to worry about getting it published... we can do it ourselves! and not only that, but we can do it as often as we want to. </para>

<para>We can use tools such as <link xlink:href="https://github.com">Github</link> to maintain our collaboration. With tools like this we are no longer limited to manual updates; all collaborators can stay up to date with what everything else is doing by downloading the content of the book and updating periodically. If there is disagreement it can be hammered out as the book is being written and read by everyone rather than at the end of the process when changes are costlier and people are invested in the book as is.<footnote><para>The XML source for this book along with all the ancillary files (Ant build files and others) are available on Github at <link xlink:href="https://github.com/caraya/docbook-epub">https://github.com/caraya/docbook-epub</link></para></footnote></para>

<para>Even the funding may be community supported. Services like <link xlink:href="http://www.kickstarter.com/">Kickstarter</link> or <link xlink:href="http://www.indiegogo.com/">Indiegogo</link> provide "crowd funding" platforms where people who are interested in your idea can invest in it even before the product is completed.</para>

<para>There are few differences between Kickstarter and Indiegogo; The biggest difference is that Indiegogo allows for partial funding. Say that we decided to raise $1000 for our book but, for whatever reason, we failed to meet the target. Kickstarter will consider the drive failed and no money will be charged to the people who did sign up. With the flexible option, Indiegogo will charge the amount raised up to that point from the people who pledged their donations.</para>

<para>Now you get no only the funding you need to get your book up and running but you also get a group of enthusiastic people who are as interested in the success of your book as you are, if not more<footnote><para>For a more detailed account of a successful Kickstarter story see Craig Mod's <link xlink:href="http://craigmod.com/journal/kickstartup/">Kickstartup</link> essay.</para></footnote>.</para>

<sect1 xml:id="why.docbook">
<title>Why Docbook?</title>

<para>Over the years <link xlink:href="http://docbook.org/">Docbook</link> has proved to be a very versatile vocabulary for book authoring. I've written training manuals and converted them to PDF, HTML and even Microsoft Help. Epub (both version 2 and 3) are another tool added to the arsenal.</para>

<para>In addition to the standard itself there are a set of XSLT style sheets that power the transformation process. These stylesheets are available from the <link xlink:href="http://sourceforge.net/projects/docbook/">Docbook Sourceforge Project</link> page. You can see the variety of formats available to convert your content into.</para>

<para>But perhaps the aspect I found out most attractive about Docbook is its community. It is self-supporting and it has evolved along with Docbook and its associated style sheets. It is welcoming and you get quick and accurate answers to your questions (always an important consideration when working with open source software)</para>
</sect1>
<sect1 xml:id="other.choices">
	<title>Is Docbook the only alternative for creating ebooks?</title>
	
	<para>No, it isn't. There are several tools we can use to create eBooks. I will only mention the tools and, where appropriate, where you can get a copy.</para>

<para><emphasis role="bold">Apple Pages</emphasis> (part of the Apple office suite along with Keynote and Numbers). It is a fairly robust word processor that has the ability to export the content of the book directly into ePub. It is Macintosh-only but I think it's worth the Investment.</para>

<para><emphasis role="bold">Sigil</emphasis> is available through their Google Code project (<link xlink:href="http://code.google.com/p/sigil/">http://code.google.com/p/sigil/</link>). Sigil  is very similar to Adobe Dreamweaver, used to create web content.  It is flexible and it has most of the tools that make valid ebooks, such as metadata editor and tools for making chapters.</para>

<para><emphasis role="bold">Adobe InDesign</emphasis> is a very powerful publishing tool. It now allows you to export your publication directly to ePub. Don't expect your InDesign document to translate 100% into ePub. With all the capabilities of InDesign that is impossible. What it is possible is to use your InDesign expertise to tailor your publication to Docbook and then do the conversion... it takes some manual work but at least it allows you to reuse your content.</para>
</sect1>
</chapter>

<chapter xml:id="docbook.creation">
<title>Creating your Docbook content</title>

<para>Now that we've talked about Why you you should use Docbook to publish your book we can get started writing.</para>

<para>We will go over some of the basics of using Docbook and then cover some customization topics. </para>

<sect1 xml:id="getting.started">
<title>Getting Started</title>

<para>The skeleton file below is all you need to get started with Docbook. You can copy this to a text file with the xml extension and then start to work.</para>

<example xml:id="basic.docbook">
<title>Minimal Docbook document</title>
<programlistingco>
<programlisting>&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?&gt; <co xml:id="xml.decl"/>
&lt;book <co xml:id="docbook.root"/>
	xmlns='http://docbook.org/ns/docbook' <co xml:id="default.namespace"/>
	xmlns:xlink='http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink' <co xml:id="xlink.namespace"/>
	version="5.0" xml:lang="en"&gt;
&lt;title&gt;Using From Docbook to ePub and Kindle too&lt;/title&gt; <co xml:id="book.title"/>
&lt;info&gt;
	&lt;author&gt; <co xml:id="docbook.author"/>
		&lt;personname&gt;
			&lt;firstname&gt;Carlos&lt;/firstname&gt;
			&lt;surname&gt;Araya&lt;/surname&gt;
		&lt;/personname&gt;
	&lt;/author&gt;
	&lt;/info&gt;
&lt;chapter&gt;
&lt;title&gt;Required Title&lt;/title&gt; <co xml:id="chapter.title"/>

&lt;para&gt;Required paragraph.&lt;/para&gt; <co xml:id="chapter.para"/>

&lt;/chapter&gt;
&lt;/book&gt;
</programlisting>
<calloutlist>
	<callout arearefs="xml.decl"><para>The Docbook file is an XML document and this marks it as such.</para></callout>
	<callout arearefs="docbook.root"><para>This is the root of the Docbook document.</para></callout>
	<callout arearefs="default.namespace"><para>The namespace declaration without a prefix will be used for all elements without an explicit prefix. This means that all elements without a prefix are, by default, in the Docbook namespace.</para></callout>
	<callout arearefs="xlink.namespace"><para>We define xlink explicitly. Xlink is used in the &lt;link&gt; element to create hyperlinks.</para></callout>
	<callout arearefs="docbook.author"><para>This is how Docbook expects to see an author.</para></callout>
    <callout arearefs="chapter.title chapter.para"><para>These elements are requires inside a Docbook chapter.</para></callout>
</calloutlist>
</programlistingco>
</example>

<para>With that basic structure let's get to work.</para>

<sect2 xml:id="creating.chapters">
<title>Creating chapters</title>

<para>A book has one or more chapters. They are normally used to separate the big parts of your content.</para>

<para>The Docbook syntax to create a chapter is shown below</para>

<example id="ch.sample">
<title>Sample Docbook Chapter</title>
<programlisting>
&lt;chapter&gt;
&lt;title&gt;Required Title&lt;/title&gt; 

&lt;para&gt;Required paragraph.&lt;/para&gt;

&lt;/chapter&gt;
</programlisting>
</example>

<para><tag>&lt;title&gt;</tag> and at least one paragraph (<tag>&lt;para&gt;</tag>) are required.</para>

</sect2>


<sect2 xml:id="creating.headings">
<title>Creating headings</title>

<para>Just like chapters are used to organize the big units of content in your book headings can be used to organize the content inside the chapter. They are equivalent to the <tag>&lt;h1&gt;</tag> to <tag>&lt;h6&gt;</tag> heading tags. The main difference is that in Docbook you wrap the heading tag around the content. For example, the example below will generate an H1 tag in the resulting HTML file.</para>

<example xml:id="sect.example">
<title>Examples of a section in a Docbook document.</title>
<programlisting>&lt;sect1 xml:id="creating.chapters"&gt;
&lt;title&gt;Creating chapters&lt;/title&gt;

&lt;para&gt;The content that goes under the &lt;h1&gt; tag goes here.&lt;/para&gt;
&lt;/sect1&gt;
</programlisting>
</example>

<para>The difference is that, in HTML, you can jump directly to a level 2 or level 3 heading. In Docbook the heading hierarchy has to be maintained. Your first sect tag has to be a level 1 and so on. This is required.</para>
</sect2>

<sect2 xml:id="adding.text">
<title>Adding text content.</title>

<para>The basic unit of content is the paragraph. It is as simple as doing the following:</para>

<example xml:id="para.example">
<title>Examples of a paragraph in a Docbook document.</title>
<programlisting>&lt;para&gt;The paragraph is the basic unit of text in a Docbook document&lt;/para&gt;
</programlisting>
</example>

<para>The examples below include additional elements that we can add inside a paragraph.</para> 

<sect3 xml:id="bold.italics">
<title>Bold and Italics</title>

<para>Both bold and italics in a Docbook document use the same tag, &lt;emphasis&gt;. To get a bold effect we need to add a role to our emphasis tag; something like this &lt;emphasis role="bold"&gt;; Italics are obtained with the regular &lt;emphasis&gt; tag.</para>    

<para>In the example below, the word paragraph will appear in bold while the word Docbook will appear in italics.</para>

<example xml:id="bold.italic.example">
<title>Examples of a bold of italics emphasis in a Docbook paragraph.</title>
<programlisting>&lt;para&gt;The &lt;emphasis role="bold">paragraph&lt;role&gt; is the basic unit of text in a &lt;emphasis&gt;Docbook&lt;/emphasis&gt; document&lt;/para&gt;
</programlisting>
</example>
</sect3>

<sect3 xml:id="hyperlinks">
<title>Hyperlinks</title>
<para></para>

<example xml:id="link.example">
<title>Examples of hyperlink in a Docbook paragraph.</title>
<programlisting>&lt;para&gt;The paragraph is the basic unit of text in a &lt;link xlink:href="http://docbook.org"&gt;Docbook&lt;link&gt; document &lt;/para&gt;
</programlisting>
</example>
</sect3>
</sect2>

<sect2 xml.id="images">
<title>Images</title>

<para>Images take a little bit of extra work to create with Docbook. As you can see below the image is wrapped around a <tag>&lt;mediaobject&gt;tag</tag> that also contains the caption for the image we are inserting. Notice that we </para>
<example xml:id="image.example">
<title>An image in Docbook</title>
<programlisting>&lt;mediaobject&gt;
    &lt;imageobject condition="web"&gt;
          &lt;imagedata fileref="tower.png" format="PNG"/&gt;
      &lt;/imageobject&gt;
      &lt;caption&gt;
          &lt;para&gt;Designed by Gustave Eiffel in 1889, The Eiffel Tower is one of the most widely recognized buildings in the world.&lt;/para&gt;
      &lt;/caption&gt;
&lt;/mediaobject&gt;
</programlisting>
</example>
</sect2>


<sect2 xml:id="audio.video">
<title>Adding multimedia: audio and video.</title>

<para>One of the coolest things, IMO, about EPub3</para>
<example xml:id="video.example">
<title>Adding a video to Docbook.</title>
<programlisting>&lt;mediaobject&gt;
&lt;videoobject&gt;
	&lt;videodata controls="controls" fileref="video/do-lectures.mp4"/&gt;
&lt;/videoobject&gt;
&lt;imageobject role="poster"&gt;
	&lt;imagedata fileref="video/do-lectures.png"/&gt;
&lt;/imageobject&gt;
&lt;textobject&gt;
	&lt;para&gt;Craig Mod presenting at the Do Lecture in 2010&lt;/para&gt;
&lt;/textobject&gt;
&lt;/mediaobject&gt;
</programlisting>
</example>
<para></para>
</sect2>


<sect2 xml:id="making.cover">
<title>Making sure we have a cover</title>

<para>Aren't the covers of the ebooks you see online awesome?</para> 

<para>You should get a cover in your EPUB output if you add a mediaobject with the role attribute set to "cover" to your bookinfo/articleinfo block. In DocBook 5.0, you may put the mediaobject inside a cover element, which should itself be inside an &lt;info> block.</para>
</sect2>

<!--
<sect1>
<title>Customizations</title>
<subtitle>Changing the way your book looks</subtitle>
<para>Content is required in chapters too.</para>

<sect2>
	<title>The relatively simple</title>
	<para></para>
</sect2>

<sect2>
	<title>The not-so-simple</title>
	<para>Content is required in chapters too.</para>
</sect2>
-->
</sect1>
</chapter>

<chapter xml:id="transformation">
<title>Converting the XML into different formats</title>
	<para>something interesting goes here</para>

<sect1 xml:id="convert.epub2">
	<title>Converting to ePub 2</title>
	<para>Content is required in chapters too.</para>
</sect1>

<sect1 xml:id="convert.epub3">
<title>Making an ePub3 ebook </title>
	<para>Content is required in chapters too.</para>
</sect1>

<sect1 xml:id="convert.kindle">
<title>Let's not forget the Kindle</title>
	<para>Content is required in chapters too.</para>
</sect1>
</chapter>


<chapter xml:id="automation">
<title>Automating the process</title>
<subtitle>Make the computer work for you</subtitle>

<para>During all the development of the ebooks using Docbook I kept asking myself the question "Is there an easier way to do this? There is, it has a steep initial development but it saves lots of time in the long run. I've finally settled on Apache Ant for the task.</para>

<sect1 xml:id="apache.ant">
	<title>Apache Ant and making things easier on yourself</title>
	
	<para>I love Apache Ant!</para>
	
	<para>It is a cross-platform tool written in Java originally created to automate software development tasks it can be used for just about everything Make can and then some more. I've used Ant for a number of years and have developed a number of scripts for working with Docbook. The latest iteration of the build file will be covered in this chapter in detail. </para>

	<para>The basic requirements for running this build file are:</para>
	
	<itemizedlist>
		<listitem>
		    <para>A Java Runtime Engine (JRE) or Java Development Kit (JDK) available from <link xlink:href="http://www.java.com/en/download/index.jsp">http://www.java.com/en/download/index.jsp</link>.</para></listitem>
		<listitem>
		    <para>Apache Ant binary distribution available from <link xlink:href="http://ant.apache.org/bindownload.cgi">http://ant.apache.org/bindownload.cgi</link>. This will download the software from the closest Apache mirror to your location.</para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
		    <para><link xlink:href="http://ant-contrib.sourceforge.net/">Ant-Contrib</link> Tasks. These additions to Ant provide with new tasks that make it easier to create conditional actions. There are more tasks but we only use if and, in a future version of the build file, switch for conditional task execution.</para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
		    <para>XMLlint, a part of the <link xlink:href="http://xmlsoft.org">XML C toolkit and Library of Gnome</link>. Most Unix-like systems (Macintosh OS X and Linux) have this software already installed.</para>
		    <para>Binary installations for Windows machines can be downloaded from the <link xlink:href="http://www.zlatkovic.com/libxml.en.html">maintainer's website</link>. These binary distributions don't require compilation.</para></listitem>
		<listitem>
		    <para><link xlink:href="http://xmlsoft.org/xslt/xsltproc2.html">XSLTProc</link>, part of the XSLT library. This library lives on top of <link xlink:hef="http://xmlsoft.org/">LibXML</link>. Install LibXML first and then LibXSLT otherwise XSLTProc will not work. You need to have LibXML installed before installing LibXSLT and XSLTProc.</para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
		    <para><link xlink:href="http://code.google.com/p/epubcheck/">epubcheck</link> (current version is 3.0b5) used to validate the resulting epub document.</para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
		    <para><link xlink:href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/feature.html/?docId=1000765211">Kindlegen</link>. An application from Amazon used to convert epub books into the mobi format used by the Kindle.</para>
		</listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
		
	<para>I chose Ant because it is cross platform. As long as we have the tools listed above it won't matter if we are on a Macintosh or Windows system. The targets and tasks will run in whatever system Ant and Java are installed in.</para>
	
<sect2 xml:id="ant.overview">
	<title>A quick overview of Ant</title>
	
	<para>In order to make better sense of the targets and tasks below it is important to understand Ant and its vocabulary. It is by no means a complete tutorial on Ant. It is meant to cover the basics and provide the background needed to interact with the Build file and modify it if necessary.</para>
	
	<para>The introduction to the <link xlink:href="http://ant.apache.org/manual/">Ant manual</link> explains why Ant is a good solution:</para>

	<blockquote>
		<para>Why another build tool when there is already make, gnumake, nmake, jam, and others? Because all those tools have limitations that Ant's original author couldn't live with when developing software across multiple platforms. Make-like tools are inherently shell-based: they evaluate a set of dependencies, then execute commands not unlike what you would issue on a shell. This means that you can easily extend these tools by using or writing any program for the OS that you are working on; however, this also means that you limit yourself to the OS, or at least the OS type, such as Unix, that you are working on.</para>
	</blockquote>
	
	<para>There are three main concepts to know about Ant build files:</para>

	<orderedlist>
		<listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">Tasks</emphasis> - are your instructions, like java, move, copy. We group 1 or more tasks into targets. See</para></listitem>
		<listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">Targets</emphasis> – are groups of tasks put together to accomplish a goal like creating a PDF version of the XML source. Think of targets as modules in Ruby or functions in Java or Python. They can be reused.</para></listitem>
		<listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">Properties</emphasis> – define variables in your build file which may change from project to project. We call these properties from within the build file by using the syntax ${name_of_property}.</para></listitem>
	</orderedlist>
	
	<para>For the example build file we will make the following assumptions:  We have a property called src_file that will hold the location of our xml file and a single target that will use xsltproc to create a single-file HTML version of our document. the build file may look like this:</para>

<example xml:id="ant.basic.docbook">
<title>Sample Ant Project</title>
<programlistingco>
<programlisting>&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?&gt; <co xml:id="ant.xml.decl"/>
&lt;project name="epub" default="make" basedir="."&gt; <co xml:id="ant.project.def"/>
&lt;property name="src_file" value="docbook-howto"/&gt; <co xml:id="ant.property.def"/>    
&lt;target name="make"&gt; <co xml:id="ant.target.def"/>
	&lt;exec executable="xsltproc"&gt;
		&lt;arg line="/usr/local/docbook/xhtml/docbook.xsl ${src_file}"/&gt; <co xml:id="ex.prop.use"/>
	&lt;/exec&gt;
&lt;/target&gt;
&lt;target name="clean"&gt;
    &lt;delete dir="bin"/&gt;
&lt;/target&gt;
</programlisting>
<calloutlist>
	<callout arearefs="ant.xml.decl"><para>The build file is an XML document and this marks it as such.</para></callout>
	<callout arearefs="ant.project.def"><para>This defines the project we will work on.</para></callout>
	<callout arearefs="ant.property.def"><para>Property definition for src_file.</para></callout>
	<callout arearefs="ant.target.def"><para>we define the target called make and inside we run xsltproc</para></callout>
	<callout arearefs="ex.prop.use"><para>As part of the arguments to xsltproc we use the call to src_file as ${src_file}</para></callout>
</calloutlist>
</programlistingco>
</example>

    <para>In order to use these tasks we just call them using <command>ant</command> and the name of the target we want to run. In order to execute the clean target we would use <command>ant clean</command>. If we call ant without arguments it will execute the task listed under the project's default element. For our sample project, calling <command>ant</command> it will execute the make task because it is the default listed under the project.</para>
    
<!-- Beef this up -->    
<para>This introduction barely scratches the surface of what Ant is and what it can do. A god tutorial can be found at <link xlink:href="http://www.comscigate.com/ant/Automate_your_build_process_using_Java_and_Ant.htm">http://www.comscigate.com/ant/Automate_your_build_process_using_Java_and_Ant.htm</link>.</para>
</sect2>
</sect1>

<sect1 xml:id="ant.setup">
	<title>Setting everything up</title>

<para>We begin our file by declaring our root element and setting properties for use throughout the build file. We also declare that we will use the if task from the ant-contrib project. </para>

<para>We also setup a default target (in this case docbook-single) and a base directory (the directory where the build file is located). If we call ant without telling it what task to run it will execute the default task assigned to the project (docbook-single in this case). </para>

<example xml:id="script.setup">
<title>Setting up the Ant Project</title>
<programlisting>&lt;project name="eBook" default="docbook-single" basedir="."&gt;
&lt;!-- Required for the IF Task --&gt;
&lt;taskdef resource="net/sf/antcontrib/antcontrib.properties"/&gt;

&lt;!-- Change the value of src_file to the name of your ebook file 
without extension--&gt;
&lt;property name="src_file" value="docbook-howto"/&gt;

&lt;!-- 
	Change the properties below to the full path of the respective 
	tools on your system. 
	
	This should work on Windows, Mac and Linux since Ant is
	crossplatform... I hope
--&gt;
&lt;property name="saxon_bin" value="/usr/local/java/saxon.jar"/&gt;
&lt;property name="fop_bin" value="/usr/local/java/fop/fop"/&gt;
&lt;property name="epubcheck_bin" value="/usr/local/java/epubcheck/\
    epubcheck-3.0b4.jar"/&gt;
&lt;property name="kindlegen_bin" value="/usr/local/kindlegen/kindlegen"/&gt;
&lt;property name="xsltproc_bin" value="/usr/bin/xsltproc"/&gt;
&lt;property name="xmllint_bin" value="/usr/bin/xmllint"/&gt;

&lt;!-- set global properties for this build --&gt;
&lt;!-- Destination directories for the HTML targets--&gt;
&lt;property name="dest_html2"  value="html_content"/&gt; 
&lt;property name="dest"  value="ebook-content"/&gt; 
&lt;!-- locations for ancillary directories for HTML content--&gt;
&lt;property name="css"  value="${dest}/css"/&gt; 
&lt;property name="js"  value="${dest}/js"/&gt; 
&lt;property name="images"  value="${dest}/images"/&gt; 

&lt;!-- Path to stylesheets --&gt;
&lt;property name="xslt1_xhtml" 
        value="/usr/local/docbook/1.0/xslt/xhtml/"/&gt;
&lt;property name="xslt2_xhtml" 
        value="/usr/local/docbook/2.0/release/2.0.3/xslt/base/html/"/&gt;
</programlisting>
</example>
</sect1>
<sect1 xml:id="ant.basic.tasks">
	<title>Basic Tasks</title>

<para>Here is a rundown of the basic tasks that we need to complete.</para>
<sect2 xml:id="ant.epub2">
	<title>EPub 2</title>

<para>EPub 2 is the older version of the standard and, as such, has a more limited set of features than the more recent EPub 3 standard (see below). This target and the one below make extensive use of the auxiliary tasks listed under <emphasis>Secondary Targets</emphasis>. We set up the targets like this because there may be times when we want to execute the secondary targets on their own without generating the enter epub file again.</para>

<para>For example: Let's say that we made a change to the CSS stylesheets for the book. We could generate the HTML files all over again by calling the epub2 task or we could just copy the CSS file using the copy-css target (called as part of copy-resources) and then epub-zip to compress it all together and epub-check to validate the resulting EPub document.</para>

<example xml:id="task.epub2">
<title>EPub 2 Ant target</title>
<programlisting>&lt;target name="epub2"&gt;
&lt;!-- Remove prior versions of the content we're generating --&gt;
&lt;antcall target="epub-clean"/&gt;
&lt;!-- Validate XML --&gt;
&lt;antcall target="validate-xml"/&gt;
&lt;!-- Run the stylesheet conversion --&gt;
&lt;exec executable="${xsltproc_bin}"&gt;
	&lt;arg line="${docbook_path}epub/docbook.xsl ${src_file}.xml"/&gt;
&lt;/exec&gt;
&lt;!-- Create mimetype file, required per epub spec --&gt;
&lt;antcall target="make-mime"/&gt;
&lt;!-- zips the fills for the epub --&gt;
&lt;antcall target="epub-zip"/&gt;
&lt;!-- Runs epubcheck on the epub file --&gt;
&lt;antcall target="epub-check"/&gt;
&lt;!-- Creates a Kindle version of the book 
based on the epub file we just created --&gt;
&lt;antcall target="make-kindle"/&gt;
&lt;/target&gt;
</programlisting>
</example>

<para>The antcall task is used to call other targets inside the same build file. Think of it as a subroutine call in languages like basic. </para>

<para>We use antcall to delete all existing files from prior eBook generation. Because we use the same directory structure for both EPub 2 and EPub 3 we have to make sure we start clean.</para> 

<para>We next validate the XML document itself using a call to xmllint.</para>

<para>The core of this target is to execute xsltproc to generate the xhtml needed for the EPub document. One file that the style sheets don't create is the mimetype text file required for EPub books to validate. </para>

<para>We are now ready to zip the file following the instructions for generating a zip file by adding the mimetype first without compression and then adding the rest of the files compressed. </para>

<para>We validate the file using EPubcheck available from <link xlink:href="http://code.google.com/p/epubcheck/">Googlecode</link>.</para>

<para>Assuming the book validates we run our last target, we make a kindle version of the book.</para>
</sect2>

<sect2 xml:id="ant.epub3">
	<title>EPub 3</title>

<para>The latest released version of the EPub specification adds more multimedia functionality to EPub books. We can add video, audio and change the way we style our text.</para>

<example xml:id="task.epub3">
<title>EPub 3 Ant target</title>
<programlisting>&lt;target name="epub3"&gt;
&lt;!-- Remove prior versions of the content we're generating --&gt;
&lt;antcall target="epub-clean"/&gt;
&lt;!-- Validate XML --&gt;
&lt;antcall target="validate-xml"/&gt;
&lt;!-- Run the xslt transformation... we should be able to 
use the XSLT ant task but xsltproc is faster --&gt;
&lt;exec executable="${xsltproc_bin}"&gt;
	&lt;arg line="--stringparam base.dir OEBPS/ 
        ${docbook_path}epub3/carlos-chunk.xsl 
        ${src_file}.xml"/&gt;
&lt;/exec&gt;
&lt;!-- Copy media resources --&gt;
&lt;antcall target="copy-resources"/&gt;
&lt;!-- zips the fils for the epub --&gt;
&lt;antcall target="epub-zip"/&gt;
&lt;!-- Runs epubcheck on the epub file --&gt;
&lt;antcall target="epub-check"/&gt;
&lt;/target&gt;
</programlisting>
</example>

<para>There are a few differences between the epub2 and epub3 targets. They will be noted below.</para>

<para>In order to reuse the tasks we created for our work with EPub 2 we use the antcall task to call other targets inside the same build file. In this way we avoid duplication and keep the build file from getting bloated with duplicate tasks.</para>

<para>The first task to delete all existing files from prior eBook generation to make sure we are working with clean sources in case we need to edit the file manually. </para>

<para>We next validate the XML document itself using a call to xmllint.</para>

<para>The core of this target is to execute xsltproc to generate the xhtml needed for the EPub document. Rather than call the stock XSL stylesheet we call a custom one (carlos-chunk.xsl) in order to customize the result of the ebook. </para>

<para>How to create customization layers and what you can do with them is outside the scope of this book. If you're interested in finding out more, you can check Bob Stayton's book <link xlink:href="http://sagehill.net/docbookxsl/index.html">XSL: The Complete Guide</link>. The main task of this customization layer is to add item elements to a file that gets zipped as part of the eBook archive. </para>

<para>We don't need to worry about the mimetype file as it is created by the EPub3 stylesheets (hence the reason we don't add the make-mime target to epub3.)</para>

<para>We copy all the resources (CSS, JavaScript, font files and images) into the eBook directory. We need to be careful when copying the content; ePub validation will fail if either the file exists in the zipped archive but is not referenced in the manifest or if the file is referenced in the manifest but doesn't exist in the zipped archive.  </para>

<para>We ended up creating a condition where we ask Ant: "If the directory (CSS, for example) exists then copy its content into the corresponding directory inside OEBPS (our eBook content directory), otherwise skip it.  Then do the same for the remaining directories (JS, video and images). EPubcheck, our EPub validator is very picky so we need to be very careful when building our ebook content.</para>

<para>We are now ready to zip the file following the instructions for generating a zip file by adding the mimetype first without compression and then adding the rest of the files compressed. </para>

<para>We validate the file using EPubcheck. We use the same software to validate both version 2 and 3 files. </para>
</sect2>
</sect1>

<sect1 xml:id="ant.epub.support">
	<title>EPub support</title>

<para>Now for the supporting cast. Some of these tasks get called from the main tasks listed above and others are mean to be called from the command line. I'm a lazy coder and that has expanded into my writing as well; why use 4 commands when you can use only one call to Ant to accomplish the same thing?. </para>

<sect2 xml:id="ant.make.mime">
	<title>make-mime</title>

<para>epub2 calls this target to create a mimetype file to add to the zipped EPub book. this is a requirement of the EPub specifications. For some reason EPub 3 creates this file for you. </para>

<example xml:id="task.make-mime">
<title>make-mime Ant target</title>
<programlisting>&lt;target name="make-mime"&gt;
&lt;!-- Creates mimetype file as required by epub spec--&gt;
&lt;echo file="mimetype"&gt;application/epub+zip&lt;/echo&gt;
&lt;/target&gt;
</programlisting>
</example>
</sect2>
<sect2 xml:id="ant.make.kindle">
	<title>make-kindle</title>

<para>Given a valid EPub 2 zip file this target will create and validate the mobi file for Kindle and other devices supporting the format. This is a proprietary tool and may add encryption to the file (don't have a way verify this without a Kindle device)</para>

<para>This is an Ant wrapper around the kindlegen application available from Amazon.</para>

<example xml:id="task.make-kindle">
<title>make-kindle Ant target</title>
<programlisting>&lt;target name="make-kindle"&gt;
&lt;exec executable="${kindlegen_bin}"&gt;
	&lt;arg line="${src_file}.epub"/&gt;
&lt;/exec&gt;
&lt;/target&gt;
</programlisting>
</example>
</sect2>
<sect2 xml:id="ant.epub.zip">
	<title>epub-zip</title>
	
<para>This target does a lot of the heavy lifting for the EPub generation process. We use the system's zip tool to create the EPUB file in two steps:</para>

<orderedlist>
    <listitem>We first add the mimetype file to the zip archive without compression. Per the EPub specification the mimetype file has to appear first in the EPUB archive.</listitem>
    <listitem>We then add the rest of the files to the archive with regular compression settings.</listitem>
</orderedlist>

<example xml:id="task.epub-zip">
<title>epub-zip Ant target</title>
<programlisting>&lt;target name="epub-zip"&gt;
&lt;!-- We use exec zip because I can't example out if the 
     builtin zip task conforms to what ePub expects --&gt;
&lt;!-- Zip the mimetype first without compression as required--&gt;
&lt;exec executable="zip"&gt;
	&lt;arg line="-X0 ${src_file}.epub mimetype"/&gt;
&lt;/exec&gt;
&lt;!-- Then zip the other files into the zip/epub archive --&gt;
&lt;exec executable="zip"&gt;
	&lt;arg line="-r -X9 ${src_file}.epub META-INF OEBPS"/&gt;
&lt;/exec&gt;
&lt;/target&gt;
</programlisting>
</example>
</sect2>

<sect2 xml:id="ant.epub.check">
	<title>epub-check</title>

<para>This target executes the epubcheck application available from its Googlecode project. It validates that the file conforms to the EPub specification (either version 2 or 3) and will report warnings or errors to standard output (most often your screen).</para> 

<example xml:id="task.epub-check">
<title>epub-check Ant target</title>
<programlisting>&lt;target name="epub-check"&gt;
&lt;java jar="${epubcheck_bin}" fork="true" failonerror="true" 
    maxmemory="128m"&gt;
	&lt;arg value="${src_file}.epub"/&gt;
&lt;/java&gt;
&lt;/target&gt;
</programlisting>
</example>
</sect2>
</sect1>
<sect1 xml:id="ant.copying.resources">
	<title>Copying Resources</title>
	
<para>The following tasks copy our resources to the EBook directory (OEBPS). We have a global task that will, in turn call the individual copy tasks, and then we have the individual ones. Again, we have sacrificed the length of the build file for flexibility as we can call the individual tasks from the command line or run them as part of the epub3 task. </para>

<sect2 xml:id="ant.copy.resources">
	<title>copy-resources</title>

<para>This is the wrapper task that will copy resources into our OEBPS directory.</para> 

<example xml:id="task.copy-resources">
<title>copy-resources Ant target</title>
<programlisting>&lt;target name="copy-resources"&gt;
&lt;!-- Macro Task to copy resouces into OEBPS--&gt;
&lt;antcall target="copy-css"/&gt;
&lt;antcall target="copy-videos"/&gt;
&lt;antcall target="copy-images"/&gt;
&lt;antcall target="copy-fonts"/&gt;
&lt;/target&gt;
</programlisting>
</example>
</sect2>

<sect2 xml:id="ant.copy.video">
	<title>copy-video</title>

<para>This target will first check if there is a video directory in our current workspace. If there is one it'll copy all files with mp4, jpg and png extensions into OEBPS/video. The images in this directory will be used as poster images for the videos. That's why we put them here and not in the images directory. </para>

<para>If the directory doesn't exist then we just print a message and move on. </para>

<para>When authoring our content we need to be sure that we remember to put the proper path to our videos. If we are the editor then we need to keep an eye for this, otherwise the videos will not work and, most likely, epubcheck will complain that there are videos referenced in the document but not available in the package. </para>

<example xml:id="task.copy-video">
<title>copy-video Ant target</title>
<programlisting>&lt;target name="copy-videos"&gt;
&lt;if&gt;
&lt;available file="video" type="dir"/&gt;
&lt;then&gt;
	&lt;copy todir="OEBPS/video"&gt;
		&lt;fileset dir="video/"&gt;
			&lt;include name="*.mp4"/&gt;
			&lt;include name="*.png"/&gt;
			&lt;include name="*.jpg"/&gt;
		&lt;/fileset&gt;
	&lt;/copy&gt;
&lt;/then&gt;
&lt;else&gt;
	&lt;echo message="No videos to copy"/&gt;
&lt;/else&gt;
&lt;/if&gt;
&lt;/target&gt;
</programlisting>
</example>
</sect2>

<sect2 xml:id="ant.copy.images">
	<title>copy-images</title>

<para>This task does with images what copy-video did with videos. We make sure that the images directory exist before we do anything to avoid epubcheck complains.</para>

<para>We support the copy of jpg, png and gif images. </para>

<example xml:id="task.copy-images">
<title>copy-images Ant target</title>
<programlisting>&lt;target name="copy-images"&gt;
&lt;if&gt;
	&lt;available file="images" type="dir"/&gt;
	&lt;then&gt;
		&lt;mkdir dir="OEBPS/images"/&gt;
		&lt;copy todir="OEBPS/images"&gt;
			&lt;fileset dir="images" casesensitive="yes"&gt;
			  &lt;include name="*.jpg"/&gt;
			  &lt;include name="*.gif"/&gt;
			  &lt;include name="*.png"/&gt;
			&lt;/fileset&gt;
		&lt;/copy&gt;
	&lt;/then&gt;
	&lt;else&gt;
		&lt;echo message="no images to copy"/&gt;
	&lt;/else&gt;
&lt;/if&gt;
&lt;/target&gt;
</programlisting>
</example>
</sect2>

<sect2 xml:id="ant.copy.fonts">
	<title>copy-fonts</title>

<para>When copying fonts we are excluding any that contain the string Callua. I'm not 100% sure that I want to use the font but, at the same time, I may. So I keep it in the directory and exclude it from the copy process. </para>

<para>Whether the fonts display properly will depend on the style sheet you create to support the font embedding process. </para>
 
<example xml:id="task.copy-fonts">
<title>copy-fonts Ant target</title>
<programlisting>&lt;target name="copy-fonts"&gt;
&lt;if&gt;
&lt;available file="type" type="dir" /&gt;
	&lt;then&gt;
		&lt;echo message="Directory exist... copying font files" /&gt;
		&lt;mkdir dir="OEBPS/type"/&gt;
		&lt;copy todir="OEBPS/type"&gt;
			 &lt;fileset dir="type/"&gt;
			     &lt;exclude name="Calluna*.*"/&gt;
			 &lt;/fileset&gt;
		&lt;/copy&gt;
	&lt;/then&gt;
	&lt;else&gt;
	&lt;!-- There are no fonts... tough luck buddy --&gt;
		&lt;echo message="There are no fonts available" /&gt;
	&lt;/else&gt;
&lt;/if&gt;	
&lt;/target&gt;
</programlisting>
</example>
</sect2>

<sect2 xml:id="ant.copy.css">
	<title>copy-css</title>

<para>When copying style sheets to out OEBPS directory we do things slightly different than what we've done so far. We are still checking if there's a css directory in our workspace but instead of copying to an equivalent directory under OEBPS we copy them to the root of our EBook content. </para>

<example xml:id="task.copy-css">
<title>copy-css Ant target</title>
<programlisting>&lt;target name="copy-css"&gt;
&lt;if&gt;
	&lt;available file="css" type="dir"/&gt;
	&lt;then&gt;
		&lt;copy todir="OEBPS"&gt;
			&lt;fileset dir="css" casesensitive="yes"&gt;
			  &lt;include name="*.css"/&gt;
			&lt;/fileset&gt;
		&lt;/copy&gt;
	&lt;/then&gt;
	&lt;else&gt;
		&lt;echo message="no style sheet to copy"/&gt;
	&lt;/else&gt;
&lt;/if&gt;
&lt;/target&gt;
</programlisting>
</example>
</sect2>
</sect1>

<sect1 xml:id="ant.validation">
	<title>Validation</title>

<para>In addition to validating the output of the Ebook and having Ant, XSLTProc and Saxon validate our content to make sure it is correct we also validate it manually using xmllint (part of the libxml project). </para>

<sect2 xml:id="ant.validate.xml">
	<title>validate-xml</title>

<para>We call xmllint and tell it to suppress its output if it's successful and not to go online to complete its validation of our xml file. </para>

<example xml:id="task.validate-xml">
<title>copy-resources Ant target</title>
<programlisting>&lt;!-- We call xmllint to make sure that the XML validates--&gt;
&lt;target name="validate-xml"&gt;
&lt;exec executable="${xmllint_bin}"&gt;
	&lt;arg line="-noent -noout ${src_file}.xml"/&gt;
&lt;/exec&gt;
&lt;/target&gt;
</programlisting>
</example>
</sect2>
</sect1>

<sect1 xml:id="ant.file.download">
	<title>File download</title>

<para>EPub 3 is still experimental, which means that it's part of the snapshot distribution of the XSLT 1.0 of the style sheets. The snapshot build is regenerated any time that a developer makes a change in Sourceforge which makes it very important to keep up to date with the releases.</para> 

<sect2 xml:id="ant.get.xsl">
	<title>get-xsl</title>

<para>The get-docbook task will do 4 things in order</para>

<orderedlist>
	<listitem>Download the snapshot from <link xlink:href="http://snapshots.docbook.org/">http://snapshots.docbook.org/</link> as docbook.zip</listitem>
	<listitem>Make a directory called docbook and unzips the download into that directory, creating a directory called docbook-xsl-ns-snapshot</listitem>
	<listitem>Move all the content from the docbook-xsl-ns-snapshot up one level to docbook.</listitem>
	<listitem>Remove the docbook-xsl-ns-snapshot directory inside docbook.</listitem>
</orderedlist>

<para>The result is that we can now simplify the path to our docbook style sheets.</para>

<para>Please don't delete docbook.zip unless it is absolutely necessary. The get task uses the timestamp on this file to decide if it has to download the snapshot again. If this file is removed the snapshot will be downloaded every time this target is executed. </para>

<example xml:id="task.get-xsl">
<title>get-xsl Ant target</title>
<programlisting>&lt;!-- Download the docbook snapshot distribution. 
	Ignore this target if you're working offline --&gt;
&lt;target name="get-xsl"&gt;
&lt;mkdir dir="docbook"/&gt;
&lt;get 
	src="http://snapshots.docbook.org/docbook-xsl-ns-snapshot.zip" 
	dest="docbook.zip"  
	verbose="true" 
	usetimestamp="true"/&gt;
&lt;unzip src="docbook.zip" dest="docbook"/&gt;
&lt;delete dir="docbook/docbook-xsl-ns-snapshot"/&gt;	
&lt;/target&gt;
</programlisting>
</example>
</sect2>
</sect1>

<sect1 xml:id="ant.cleanup">
	<title>Cleanup</title>
	
<para>I always setup tasks to clean up the working files used when creating the different versions of docbook.</para>


<sect2 xml:id="ant.epub.clean">
	<title>epub-clean</title>

<para>The final cleanup task is to remove all the files created by epub2 or epub3. We use the same directories for both versions so it is important that we clean up all the files.</para>

<example xml:id="task.epub-clean">
<title>epub-clean Ant target</title>
<programlisting>&lt;target name="epub-clean"&gt;
&lt;if&gt;
	&lt;available file="OEBPS" type="dir" /&gt;
	&lt;then&gt;
		&lt;echo message="Directory exist... deleting" /&gt;
		&lt;delete verbose="true"&gt;
			&lt;fileset dir="OEBPS" includes="*"/&gt;
			&lt;fileset dir="META-INF" includes="*"/&gt;
		&lt;/delete&gt;
		&lt;delete verbose="true" file="mimetype"/&gt;
		&lt;delete verbose="true" dir="META-INF"/&gt;
		&lt;delete verbose="true" dir="OEBPS"/&gt;
		&lt;delete verbose="true" file="${src_file}.epub"/&gt;
	&lt;/then&gt;
	&lt;else&gt;
		&lt;echo message="Directory DOES NOT exist... Nothing to delete" /&gt;
	&lt;/else&gt;
&lt;/if&gt;
&lt;/target&gt;
&lt;/project&gt;
</programlisting>
</example>

<para>We first check that the OEBPS directory exist. If it does we delete its content</para>

<para>We next delete the content of the META-INF directory</para>

<para>Next we remove the mimetype file, the OEBPS and META-INF directories and the epub file. </para>

<para>If the OEBPS directory doesn't exist we echo a message and do nothing.</para>

<para>The final thing we do is to close the project tag. This is not part of the epub-clean target but a requirement for well formed and valid XML.</para>

</sect2>
</sect1>

<sect1 xml:id="ant.final.result">
	<title>The final result</title>
		
<para>The final result can be viewed and downloaded from <link xlink:href="https://github.com/caraya/docbook-epub/blob/master/build-full.xml">my Github repository</link>.</para>
</sect1>
</chapter>

<chapter xml:id="pulishing">
<title>Publishing your content</title>

<para>This is where we talk about publishing your content yourself, publishing to Amazon and, maybe, to the iBooks store</para>
</chapter>

<bibliography>
<title>References</title>

<bibliomixed>
	<bibliomset relation='blog'>Godin, Seth.
		<title role='blog'><emphasis>The Domino Project</emphasis></title>.
	</bibliomset>
	<bibliomset relation='website'>
		[Available online] at <link xlink:href="http://sethgodin.typepad.com/seths_blog/2010/12/the-domino-project.html">http://sethgodin.typepad.com/seths_blog/2010/12/the-domino-project.html</link>.
	</bibliomset>
</bibliomixed>

<bibliomixed>
	<bibliomset relation='blog'>Godin, Seth.
		<title role='blog'><emphasis>Moving On</emphasis></title>.
	</bibliomset>
	<bibliomset relation='website'>
		[Available online] at <link xlink:href="http://sethgodin.typepad.com/seths_blog/2010/08/moving-on.html">http://sethgodin.typepad.com/seths_blog/2010/08/moving-on.html</link>.
	</bibliomset>
</bibliomixed>

<bibliomixed>
	<bibliomset relation='article'>Mod, Craig.
		<title role='article'><emphasis>Books in the age of the iPad</emphasis></title>.
	</bibliomset>
	<bibliomset relation='website'>
		[Available online] at <link xlink:href="http://craigmod.com/journal/ipad_and_books/">http://craigmod.com/journal/ipad_and_books/</link>.
	</bibliomset>
</bibliomixed>

<bibliomixed>
	<bibliomset relation='article'>Mod, Craig.
		<title role='article'><emphasis>Embracing the digital book</emphasis></title>.
	</bibliomset>
	<bibliomset relation='website'>
		[Available online] at <link xlink:href="http://craigmod.com/journal/ebooks/">http://craigmod.com/journal/ebooks/</link>.
	</bibliomset>
</bibliomixed>

<bibliomixed>
	<bibliomset relation='article'>Mod, Craig.
		<title role="article"><emphasis>Kickstartup: Successful fundraising with Kickstarter.com &amp; (re)making Art Space Tokyo</emphasis></title>.
	</bibliomset>
	<bibliomset relation='website'>
		[Available online] at <link xlink:href="http://craigmod.com/journal/kickstartup/">http://craigmod.com/journal/kickstartup/</link>.
	</bibliomset>
</bibliomixed>

<bibliomixed>
	<bibliomset relation='article'>Mod, Craig.
		<title role='article'><emphasis>The shape of our future book</emphasis></title>.
	</bibliomset>
	<bibliomset relation='website'>
		[Available online] at <link xlink:href="http://craigmod.com/satellite/our_future_book/">http://craigmod.com/satellite/our_future_book/</link>.
	</bibliomset>
</bibliomixed>

<bibliomixed>
	<bibliomset relation='blog'>Rusch, Kristine Kathryn.
		<title role='blog'><emphasis>Quality</emphasis></title>.
	</bibliomset>
	<bibliomset relation='website'>
		[Available online] at <link xlink:href="http://kriswrites.com/2012/03/21/the-business-rusch-quality/">http://kriswrites.com/2012/03/21/the-business-rusch-quality/</link>.
	</bibliomset>
</bibliomixed>

<bibliomixed>
	<bibliomset relation='book'>Stayton, Bob.
 		<title role='book'><emphasis>XSL: The Definitive Guide</emphasis></title>.
	</bibliomset>
	<bibliomset relation='website'>
		[Available online] at <link xlink:href="http://www.sagehill.net/docbookxsl/">http://www.sagehill.net/docbookxsl/</link>.
	</bibliomset>
</bibliomixed>

<bibliomixed>
	<bibliomset relation='book'>Walsh, Norman.
		<title role='book'><emphasis>DocBook 5.1: The Definitive Guide</emphasis></title>.
	</bibliomset>
	<bibliomset relation='website'>
		[Available online] at <link xlink:href="http://docbook.org/tdg51/en/html/">http://docbook.org/tdg51/en/html/</link>.
	</bibliomset>
</bibliomixed>
</bibliography>

<colophon>
<para>Draft versions of this book were produced with the Docbook XML stylesheets.</para>
</colophon>
</book>